In this section, we'll take a look at the over the firmware update implementation.
This firmware update will be implemented over the wireless local area network, and we'll simply upload
the binary file to the ISP using the web page.
So before we go deeper into details, let's talk about OTA updates in general using the IDF, so OTA
updates allow a device to update itself based on data received.
For example, over Wi-Fi, while the normal firmware is running and enabling firmware updates requires
configuring a partition table with at least two application slots called OTAs zero and Otere one, as
well as an OTA data partition and the OTA operation functions.
Write a new application firmware image to whichever OTA application slot is currently not selected for
booting.
So once the image is verified, the OTA data partition is updated to specify that this image should
be used for the next boot.
And further to the partition table, the flash of the East can contain multiple applications in different
kinds of data.
For example, calibration data, file systems, parameter storage, etc..
And for this purpose, a partition table is flash to hex eight thousand in flash memory, and each entry
of the partition table has a label, a type subtype and an offset in the flash, where the partition
is loaded.
And also, the simplest way to use the partition table is to open the project configuration or SDK config
and eclipse and choose factory up to 0.8 definitions.
As we've already done in the project configuration section.
And here is what a partition table looks like.
Here we have names, types, subtypes, upsets and sizes.
And in this table, which is the same as the one we're currently using, we have three applications.
We have the factory application at Offset X ten thousand and the next two applications or apps with
zero and 0.1 one subtypes.
And there is also a new OTA data slot, which holds the data for OTA updates.
The bootloader will check this OTA data slot to know which app to execute.
So if it is empty, the factory application will be executed.
And also, you can customize the partition table to suit your needs.
For example, if you application takes up more space, you can adjust the size and to remove the factory
application and just use only to zero and OTA one partitions if you need.
OK, now let's talk about our implementation.
The user can start the OTA update by uploading the application binary over the web page, and the firmware
update is then performed on the web server side and the web page will display the status, whether it
was successful or not.
And once the update is complete, the web page is no longer available and the SB 32 will then restart.
And we can then test the firmware update by making just a couple of simple changes, like changing the
side of the SB 32S Access Point and maybe the web page background just to verify that the new firmware
is indeed running.
So now let's discuss how we can accomplish this using the ESP IDF.
I suggest you browse the impressive documentation to get a better grasp on the OTA update topics you
as well as the API reference, check out the process overview and other features available that will
not be using in our example.
You can also find more details about the partition table here.
Take a look at the overview, as well as other details like creating partition tables.
If you're interested.
So the steps that will have to take on the Web server side starts with receiving the file from the web
page, and we'll call HTTP requests received for this.
So this API will read HTTP content.
Data from the HTTP request into the provided buffer will then have to make multiple calls to this function
each time fetching buffer length a number of bytes, while the pointer to the content data is incremented
internally by the same number.
Then we'll have to identify where the binary file content actually starts by checking the escape characters.
The slasher suggestions that are present when receiving the file from the web page and then call SPRO
to begin the e-sport begin function commences the update by writing to the specified partition.
And once successful, it allocates memory that remains in use until the SPL end function is called.
So next, we call Esposti right to write the first chunk of data that we've received from the web page.
The write function writes data to the specified partition that can be called multiple times as data
is received during the operation.
Which brings us to the next point we'll continue receiving the rest of the file by calling HTTP Request
Receive and Esposti to write until all of the content is received.
Then we'll finish the OTA update and validate the application image by calling Esposti End.
So here it's mentioned that the handle associated with the OTA update is no longer valid and that the
memory associated with it is freed regardless of the result.
And next, we'll need to configure the data from the partition table for the new boot partition by calling
each spot to set boot partition.
And here it's mentioned that after this calling, ECP restart will boot the newly configured application
partition, which brings us to the next function ESP restart.
This function will restart both CPU's.
Both the Pro and application CPUs will be restarted, and the function does not return, of course.
All right, so let's put this plan into action, and I'll see you in the programming sections.